Finding Aid for the Lucy Gage Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Lucy Gage Papers
2007
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0162
.84 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Lucy Gage was born in Portsmouth, Ohio on October 17, 1876. She took a Bachelor of Science degree from Columbia University in 1922 and continued to take classes and training in Columbia’s Teachers College over the next decade. She was a professor of early elementary education at George Peabody College in Nashville, Tennessee from 1920 until her retirement in 1942. At that time there was published in editions of the Peabody Reflector a series of sketches about her life which “show her life in the fullness of its development.” These sketches are included here in the Personal and Biographical series of the papers. Lucy Gage earned great praise and recognition for her work in early childhood education both in her teaching and professional activities. She died on October 30, 1945.
Scope and Content Note
This small collection, 11/2 Hollinger boxes (.63 linear feet), contains papers written by Miss Gage in manuscript, typescript, and carbon copy. Among them is a small autograph book made up at the time of her retirement in 1942 by her friends. Newspaper clippings about Miss Gage, many undated are included as well as a biographical paper telling of her pioneering efforts in early childhood education and legislation in Oklahoma in 1902. There is a letter from Agnes Snyder, Association for Childhood International, dated 1967 containing a bibliography of Miss Gage’s writings. It includes references to issues of the Peabody Reflector some of which do not appear in the Reflector indexes.
- Personal and Biographical
  - “Pioneering in Education” by Lucy Gage, pp. 79 - 92 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “Peabody College Greets Professor Lucy Gage” by Charles S. Pendleton, Professor of English, 2-15-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Series of Sketches in the Peabody Reflector published at her retirement in 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Lucy Gage: Childhood’s Champion” in the November 1945 Peabody Reflector, pp. 336 - 338 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Leatherbound book of notes collected for Lucy Gage’s retirement in 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tribute to Lucy Gage by Claude Hotchin, 23 September 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings ( photocopies of the originals found in Box 1, folder 7) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Publications
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bulletin National Council of Primary Education, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - History of the National Council of Primary Education, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Writings by Lucy Gage
  - “The Home and Parent Education” (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Article -“Interpreting the Kindergarten to the Community” (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Article - “Observation on the Development of Reader Ability in the Elementary Grades” (no date) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - “The School and Teacher Education” (20 pp. manuscript ) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - “ The Slow Growth of Professionalism in the Field of Education of Young Children” (manuscript and typescript copies ) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - “Supervision in Relation to Child Growth” ( 7 pages with bibliography ) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - “Women’s Part in Reconstruction of World Values” (manuscript, 19 pp.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - “The Young Child and His Education” ( manuscript pages ) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - “ The South’s Interest in Kindergarten Primary Education” (16 pp.) Address given before N.E.A. Atlanta, Georgia, July 2, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - “…celebrating twenty five years of successful training of teachers in the State of Michigan …” an address ( 7 pp.) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - “Remarks made at the Southern Progressive Education Association, Greensboro, North Carolina: A Teacher Laboratory at Peabody College, Nashville, Tennessee (manuscript, 7 pp.) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Curriculum Studies – “Division III – Education of Elementary Teachers and Workers” ( 3 pp. ); “The Arts and Skills”; “The Social Studies”; “The Graduate Program of Studies”; “Educative Materials Laboratory” (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Curriculum Studies – “A Guide to Elementary Teachers in Planning: Undergraduate Training ( the Nursery, Kindergarten, Early and Later Elementary Levels ) (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Writings by Lucy Gage
  - Curriculum Studies - “Modern Trends in Curriculum Making” ( manuscript 17 pp.) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Title page and Table of Contents, and manuscript outline from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood by Lucy Gage (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - “Life as Lived by Adults” typescript Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood, Chapter I. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - “Life As the Child Lives It” typescript Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood, Chapter II (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - “Gaps Existent Between the Life of an Adult and Child “typescript from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood, Chapter III (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - “Bridging the Gaps in the Area of Healthful Living” and “In the World of Play” typescripts from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - “ In the World of Realty” manuscript and typescript from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - “In the World of Thrift and Plenty” (manuscript); “In the World of Books” (typescript) chapters from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - “In the World of Wonder and Worship” typescript chapter from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - “ In the World of Wonder and Worship” manuscript copy of Chapter IX from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - “ In What Do Children Find Objects of Allegiance and Loyalty” manuscript chapter from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - “In What do Children Find Objects of Allegiance?” typescript chapter from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - “In the World of Arts” typescript chapter from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified chapter typescript from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript draft pages from Bridging Gaps Between Adulthood and Childhood (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - “Bridging the Gaps Between Adult and Child Values” - Address to the National Association for Childhood Education, July 11, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Notes for a talk at Scarritt College, January 12, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Fragments of notes and papers (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bibliography in a letter dated June 26, 1967 from Agnes Snyder, Association for Childhood International, of writings by and about Lucy Gage, 1912 - 1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)